Even if you accept
the belief that...
Mr Thornhill!
Good night, Eddy.
My recommendation
is still the same:
spread the good word
in as many small-time segments
as we can grab.
Why don't we colonise The Colony
one day for lunch? Roger, et cetera.
Better walk me to the Plaza.
But...!
Next? Gretchen Simons. Oh, yeah.
Send her a box of candy, 10 -
you know the kind,
wrapped in gold paper.
Say "Darling, I count the days, the
hours..." You said that last time!
"Something for your sweet tooth
and your other sweet parts." I know.
Can we take a cab? For two blocks?
I'm tired. You don't eat properly.
All right. Taxi!
I have a very sick woman here.
You don't mind, do you? Well, no...
First stop the Plaza.
Poor man. I made him a happy man.
I made him feel like a Samaritan.
He knew you were lying. Ah,
Maggie...
In the world of advertising, it's
known as 'expedient exaggeration.'
Say, do I look heavyish to you?
What? I FEEL heavyish.
Put a note on my desk: Think Thin.
Think Thin.
Make it the 59th Street entrance.
Oh, call my mother, remind her
about tonight's theatre tickets.
Dinner at Twenty-One, 7pm.
I'll have had two martinis,
so she needn't sniff my breath.
She doesn't do that! Sure she does.
You've the Skin Glow rehearsal
at noon, then lunch with Falcoln.
Where? Larry Nartles at one. Will
you check in later? Absolutely not.
Here, driver, take this lady
back where she belongs. Right.
Don't forget, call my mother
right away. I won't.
Good night, Mr Thornhill.
Good night.
Oh, wait! You can't call her,
she's at Mrs...
Good evening, Mr Thornhill.
Victor. I'm looking for Mr Weltner.
Yes, sir. Right this way.
Herman, sorry I'm a little late.
Thornhill, Bob Nelson...
Larry Wade.
We got off to a head start.
That won't last long.
You may be slow starting, but
you're a fast finisher. ..Roger?
I told my secretary to call Mother,
but she won't be able to reach her.
Why not? She's out playing bridge.
Your secretary?
No, my mother!
A telegram...
Perhaps I can send a telegram...
That's Kaplain.
I've got to get off a wire.
Can you send it?
I can't, sir.
But if you follow me...
Excuse me.
Go right through there, sir. Thanks.
What's that supposed to be?
­
Walk between us. Say nothing.
What are you talking about?
Let's go.
Where!? Who are you?
Mere errand boys
carrying concealed weapons.
No errors of judgment, please.
Come on! Is this a joke?
Yes, we will laugh in the car.
This is ridiculous!
Don't tell me where we're going.
Surprise me!
I left some friends back there.
They'll think me awfully rude.
Could we stop off at a drugstore
so I could explain that...
I'm being kidnapped.
That IS what's happening, isn't it?
Locked(!)
Who's Townsend?
Really?
Interesting(!)
Where is he?
Upstairs, dressing.
Dressing for dinner.
Tell him "Kaplain".
What are we having for dessert?
Is anyone in the library?
No.
You will wait here.
Don't hurry. I'll do some reading.
Good evening.
Not what I expected -
a little taller, more polished
than the others.
I'm SO glad you're pleased,
Mr Townsend.
But, I'm afraid, just as obvious.
Why the devil was I brought here?
Games? Must we?
Not that I mind abduction, but
I have tickets for the theatre -
a good show.
I get unreasonable about
such things.
What very expert play-acting...
Ah, Leonard, have you met
our distinguished guest?
He's a well-tailored one, isn't he?
My secretary's a great admirer
of your methods, Mr Kaplain...
Wait a minute.
Did you call me Kaplain?
I know you're a man of many names
but it IS your current one. What?
My name is Roger Thornhill.
It's never been anything else. Yes.
Obviously your friends picked up
the wrong package. Sit down,
Mr Kaplain.
I'm NOT Kaplain, whoever he is...
Excuse me. The guests are here,
dear.
I'll be with you in a few minutes.
Now, shall we get down to business?
I'm all for that.
I'd like you to tell me how much
you know of our arrangements.
Naturally, I'll pay for this.
Of course(!)
I don't really expect you
to co-operate. But the least I can
do is give you a chance to survive.
What the devil is THAT
supposed to mean?
Surprise me, Mr Kaplain. Say yes.
We KNOW where you were headed for.
I'm heading for the Wintergarden
Theatre in New York. I'm going!
Townsend, you're making
a serious mistake.
This won't lead to a happy ending,
Mr Kaplain.
I'm NOT Kaplain! Please reconsider.
We know your contacts in Pittsburgh
since Jason...committed suicide.
I've never even BEEN in Pittsburgh.
June 16, you checked into
the Sherwin Hotel
as Mr George Kaplain, California.
A week later, you registered
at the Benjamin Franklin
as Mr George Kaplain of Pittsburgh.
Aug 29, George Kaplain of Boston
registered in Detroit.
At present you're in 796, Plaza
Hotel, Mr Kaplain of Detroit.
In two days, you're due in Chicago.
And then at the Sheraton Johnston
in Rapid City, South Dakota. No.
There's little sense in maintaining
this attempt at deception.
I have a wallet of identification.
They provide you
with SUCH good ones.
It's getting late. I have guests.
Do you intend to co-operate?
A simple yes or no.
A simple no. For the simple reason
I don't know what you mean.
Give Mr Kaplain a drink, Leonard.
A pleasant journey, sir.
Scotch? Rye?
Bourbon? Vodka?
Nothing, just a ride into town.
That has been arranged.
First, a libation. Bourbon.
You drink it. I've had enough
stimulation.
It will be easier if you take it
yourself. Or we'll insist.
Cheers. >
DRUNKEN SINGING
# I've gr-own accu-sh-tomed
to my bourbon... #
It's OK, fella. I'll take the bus.
HORN HONKS
CACOPHONY OF HORNS BLOWING
POLICE SIRENS
Thanks for the lift, fellas.
I want this man examined
for intoxication.
You sh-ee, they tried to kill me.
A BIG house. They tried to kill me.
Let's go inside.
Sh-omebody call the police.
Come on, now.
Sit down.
I don't want to sit down.
I'm perfectly all right. See?
Get them. Throw the book at them.
Assault with bourbon
and a sports car.
You need a good night's sleep.
We've got a nice cell waiting.
I want a policeman!
That car was reported stolen.
Mrs Babson up on
Twining Row.
Where's the phone?
You're only allowed ONE call. Here.
Better make it to your lawyer.
52 - 80198.
What am I? A telephone operator?
52-80198.
Just a minute, please.
Here.
Hello. Mother?
Mother...thish is your son,
Roger Thornhill.
Ye-ess.
I'll find out.
Where am I? Glencove Police Station.
Glencove Police Station.
Mother, I have NOT been drinking.
These two men - they poured
a bottle of bourbon into me.
No. They didn't give me a chaser.
Oh... Come on, let's go.
I'm not finished yet. Yes, you are.
Mother, I-I got to go now.
Get my lawyer to come
and bail me out.
Tomorrow morning...
Tomorrow morning, he says.
I'll ask him.
WHO says? Sergeant Emile Klinger.
Sergeant Emile...Emile!
Sergeant Emile Klinger.
No, I don't believe it, either.
I'm all right, Mother. Good night.
THAT was Mother.
Let's go.
Here's your man, doctor.
What's your name?
Roger Thornhill.
Stick out your tongue and say Aah.
Better move back.
Aaaah.
Have you been drinking?
Doctor, I am gassed!
WHAT were you drinking? Bourbon.
These two fellas... How much
would you say that you drank?
This much.
Mr Thornhill, it is my opinion
that you are definitely intoxicated.
And I now wish a blood sample.
How disgusting.
You may refuse to permit a blood
test to be obtained, but if you...
LAWYER:
..in escaping
from his would-be assassins,
he drove as best he could.
Counsellor, how long
have you known your client?
Seven years.
Is he a reasonable man? >
Absolutely.
Huh!
Mother!
Is there credence to this story? >
Credence!
My client says this happened.
I'm certain it must have.
Sergeant, I want this investigated
by the County Detectives.
Have them come over here.
Right.
I'll set this over
for final disposition tomorrow. >
I expect you to return then. >
The Detectives will determine
if his story has any basis.
I suppose if I were brought in
here dead you still... Roger!
Well, would I make up such a story?
That is what I intend to find out,
Mr Thornhill.
Yes? Remember me?
Yes, sir. Good.
Is Mr Townsend here?
I'm sorry, he's out.
Mrs Townsend?
And you are?
County Detectives.
Come in, please.
This way, please.
This is the room.
I'll call madam.
Here's the sofa where they held me
down. They spilled bourbon.
I'll show you the stains.
They must have cleaned them off.
This is the liquor cabinet.
Scotch, gin, vodka...
..and bourbon.
I remember when it came
in bottles.
Roger! >
Dear, we were SO worried about you.
Did you get home all right?
A little pink-eyed,
but aren't we all.
It was a dull party,
you didn't miss a thing.
I NEVER saw this woman
before last night!
I'm Captain Junkett.
This is Lt Harding.
How do you do.
You're not in trouble, Roger?
Stop this...
Mrs Townsend, >
Mr Thornhill was picked up
driving while drunk,
in a stolen car.
Stolen car?
Mrs Babson's >
on Twining Row.
Roger, you were going
to call a cab.
You didn't borrow
Laura's Mercedes? No, I DIDN'T !
Mr Thornhill says he was
brought here unwillingly,
forcibly intoxicated,
then set out onto the road.
Well, Roger WAS
a bit tipsy when he arrived by cab.
She's lying!
He became worse
as the evening wore on.
He left to sleep it off.
I should have served dinner earlier.
What a performance!
Does the name George Kaplain
mean anything to you?
No.
I didn't think so.
Where's her husband?
You should be questioning him.
Can we reach him?
At the United Nations.
He's addressing
the General Assembly today.
So, he's at the General Assembly?
Sorry for the bother.
No bother at all.
Now, WAIT a minute, I...
Will you be wanting my husband?
No. That's not necessary.
You're not going to do anything!
Roger... Pay the 2.
Goodbye.
I don't see why you want me along.
You lend an air of respectability.
Don't be sarcastic, Roger.
Park yourself there.
Here goes.
Operator, do you have
a George Kaplain staying here?
..That's right.
You have? Room 796?
Ring him for me, please. You see.
I see. I hope it clears up this....
You're ruining... Shhh.
Oh, did he leave word
when he'd be back?
Really? Thank you.
Odd. He hasn't answered
his phone in two days.
Maybe he got locked in a bathroom.
Mother, do me a favour...
Put on that sweet, innocent look
you do so well, and get me the key.
Don't be ridiculous! Ten dollars.
Not for all the money in the world!
Fifty? You are disgraceful...
Car theft, drunk driving, lying
to a judge and now house-breaking!
HOTEL-breaking. It's different.
Excuse me! >
Will you want
your bedding changed, sir?
Yes...but not right now.
I only mention it, sir, because
the bed doesn't seem slept-in.
Thank you for your interest.
SHE seemed to think I'm Kaplain.
I wonder if I look like Kaplain.
Oh, look who's here. Who? Where?
Our friend who's assembling
the General Assembly.
Roger, I think we should go.
Don't be nervous. I'm not.
I'll be late for the Bridge Club.
Bulletin - Kaplain has dandruff.
In that case, I think we should go.
DOOR BUZZER
Too late.
You rang for me, sir? Yes. Come in.
What's your name? Elsie, sir.
Elsie.
Do you know who I am? Mr Kaplain.
When did you first see me?
Outside the door.
In the hall, a couple of minutes
ago. That's the first time you saw
me?
Can I help it if you're never here?
How do you know I AM Mr Kaplain?
What? How do you know?
Of course you are! This is Room 796.
So, you're the gentleman in 796.
All right, Elsie. Thanks.
Will that be all, sir? For now.
DOOR BUZZER
Valet. Oh, yes. Come in.
Will I hang it in the closet,
Mr Kaplain? Yes. Please.
Tell me...what time
did I give you that suit?
Last night. Around...around six.
Did I give it to you personally?
Why no! You called down on the phone
and said it would be in the closet.
Like you always do.
Anything wrong? No, just curious.
Here. Thanks. Thank YOU.
Pleased to meet you, Mr Kaplain.
I'm beginning to think that no-one
here has actually SEEN Kaplain.
Maybe he has his suits mended
by invisible weavers(!) Oh...
Let me see something.
I don't think that does anything
for you(!)
Ah, now, THAT'S much better.
They've mistaken me
for a much shorter man.
PHONE RINGS
Should I? Certainly not!
Hold that.
Hello.
'Good to find you in, Mr Kaplain.'
Who is this?
'We met only last night
and you do not recognise my voice?'
Yes, I know who you are.
And I'm NOT Mr Kaplain.
'You answer his phone, you live
in his room, yet you are not him(!)
'We are pleased to find you in.'
HANGS UP
Hello, operator. Operator.
'Yes?' This is Mr Thorn...Kaplain
in 796.
That call, where did it come from?
'I'll check.' Hurry!
Who was it? One of the men
who tried to kill me. Oh, yes(!)
Operator? 'Mr Kaplain, that call
came from the lobby, sir.' What!?
They're probably on their way up!
Let's get out!
I'd like to meet these killers.
You gentlemen
aren't REALLY trying to kill my son?
EVERYONE BEGINS TO LAUGH
LIFT ATTENDANT:
Lobby, please. Watch your step.
Gentlemen, please! Ladies first.
Come along.
Roger!
Will you be home for dinner?
Where to? Just keep going.
Take me to the United Nations. OK.
The General Assembly building. OK.
I'm being followed.
Can you do anything? Yes. DO it.
May I help you, sir? Yes, please.
Where will I find Mr Townsend?
Mr Townsend of UNECO?
Did you have an appointment, sir?
Well...yes. He expects me.
Your name, please. My name? Please.
Kaplain. George Kaplain.
One moment, please.
Wait at the corner of 47th.
Give this to an attendant in
the public lounge. She will page
him for you. Thank you very much.
of the Swiss Observers Office.
Mr Bernardi,
Page Mr Lester Townsend, please.
Certainly, Mr Kaplain.
Mr Townsend of UNECO.
desk of the public lounge.
You paged me?
Mr Kaplain. Yes.
You wanted to see Mr Townsend.
How do you do, Mr Kaplain?
THIS isn't Mr Townsend.
Yes, it is.
There must be some mistake.
Mr LESTER Townsend? That's me.
Are you the Townsend that lives in
Glen Cove? Yes. Are we neighbours?
A large red-bricked house
with a tree-lined drive? That's it.
Were you at home last night?
In Glen Cove? Yes.
I've been staying in my apartment
in town. And Mrs Townsend?
My wife has been dead for many
years.
Forgive me. But who are the people
living in your house?
What people? The house is closed up.
There's just a gardener left there.
Now, who are you? What do you want?
Eh...please, just...
Do you know this man? Ohhh!
He's got a knife!
Look out!
I had nothing to do with this.
Don't come any nearer. Get back!
"The photo has been identified
as that of Roger Thornhill
"indicating that the name
of George Kaplain, which he used,
was false.
"A possible motive for the slaying
was suggested by the discovery
"that Thornhill appeared earlier
at a police court charged
with drunk-driving.
"In his defence he charged
that Mr Townsend had tried
to kill him the night before."
What about that!
­
Does anyone know this Thornhill?
Not me.
Never heard of him.
Sir? >
Apparently he was mistaken
for George Kaplain.
George Kaplain doesn't exist.
But it happened.
­
Dam's men must have grabbed him.
He was in Lester Townsend's house.
And the unsuspecting
Mr Townsend dies.
C'est la guerre.
So, how is it I feel like laughing?
What will we do?
About Mr Thornhill?
We...we do nothing.
Nothing?
Nothing.
Or we could congratulate ourselves
on our stroke of good fortune.
Our nonexistent decoy, created
to divert suspicion from our
actual agent, becomes a live decoy.
But how long do you think
he'll STAY live? That's his problem.
I KNOW what she means.
We can't let him be killed. >
What can we do to save him
without endangering our own agent?
Isn't that a wee bit callous?
My dear woman, it's not callous.
We didn't invent our nonexistent
man, George Kaplain, establish
elaborate behaviour patterns,
or move his prop belongings around
hotels for our own amusement.
We created George Kaplain,
and successfully convinced Vandamm
that this was an agent,
for a reason.
Nobody's denying that! Very well.
If we make a move to suggest
that there is NO George Kaplain,
give any hint to Vandamm
that he is pursuing a decoy,
then our agent,
working under his very nose,
will face suspicion, exposure,
AND assassination. Like
the two others who went before.
Goodbye, Mr Thornhill,
wherever you are.
TANNOY:
'..the Twentieth Century Limited,
due to leave at 6pm, for Chicago.'
Yes... Yes, dear, I know.
Listen, Mother. I CALLED the Plaza.
Kaplain checked out. He went
to the Hotel Ambassador in Chicago.
I CAN'T go to the police. Not yet.
You saw the papers - my prints
are on the knife, I'm a car thief,
I murdered a man for revenge.
I won't have a chance
until I find George Kaplain.
No, dear, the train. It's safer.
There's no place to hide on a plane
if I'm recognised.
You want me to jump from a plane?
Yes. Well, thank you so much,
Mother. Bye.
TANNOY:
'The Twentieth Century
leaves at 6pm.'
Yeah? A bedroom on the Twentieth
Century. It leaves in five minutes.
I know. I think
they're all sold out.
Sold out? You can always go coach.
I can't. When is the next train?
Nothing till ten. You in a hurry?
Could you call them?
Something wrong with your eyes?
They're sensitive to questions.
Will you call them? Sure.
Don't go away.
He's at Window 15, Upper Level.
Hurry.
You're in luck, mister...
Ticket? I'm seeing some friends off.
I'll have to know the name and...
Just a minute!
Oh!
I'm sorry. I'm sorry. My fault.
Sorry.
He went that way.
I think he got off.
ALL ABOARD ! >
Thank you. It's quite all right.
SEVEN parking tickets. Oh.
TRAIN BEGINS TO MOVE
Good evening, sir. For one? Please.
Cocktail before dinner?
Yes, please. A Gibson.
Well, here we are again.
Yes.
Do you recommend anything?
The brook trout. It's...quite good.
Brook - trout.
Thank you. Yes, sir.
I know. I look vaguely familiar.
Yes. You feel you've seen me
somewhere before. Mm'hm.
I have that effect - something
about my face.
It's a nice face.
Think so?
I wouldn't say it if I didn't.
Oh, you're THAT type. What type?
Honest. Not really.
Good, honest women frighten me.
Why? Somehow they put me
at a disadvantage.
Because you're dishonest with them?
Exactly. Like the parking tickets?
What I mean is...the moment I meet
an attractive woman, I have to hide
my desire to make love to her.
Why conceal it?
She may find the idea objectionable.
Then again, she might not.
How lucky I am to be seated here.
Luck had nothing to do with it.
Fate?
I tipped the steward 5 to seat you
here if you should come in.
Is that a proposition?
I never discuss love
on an empty stomach.
You've already eaten.
But you haven't.
Don't you think it's time
we were introduced?
I'm Eve Kendall. I'm 26
and unmarried.
Now you know everything. What do you
do besides lure men to their doom?
I'm an industrial designer.
Jack Phillips, western sales
manager for Kingby Electronics.
You're not. You're Roger Thornhill.
You're wanted for murder
on every front page in America.
Don't be so modest. Ooops!
Don't worry. I won't say a word.
How come?
I told you...it's a nice face.
Is that all? It's going to be
a long night.
True.
I'm not enjoying the book I started.
Ah...
Know what I mean?
Now, let me think...
Yes, I know EXACTLY what you mean.
That's my trademark - "ROT".
What does the O stand for?
Nothing.
I'd invite you to my bedroom
IF I had a bedroom. A roommate?
Nothing. No ticket.
I've been playing hide and seek
with the conductor.
How awkward.
I have no place to sleep.
I have a large drawing room.
That doesn't seem quite fair.
Drawing room E, Car 39-01.
Such a nice number.
Easy to remember.
Thirty-nine, oh-one.
See.
No luggage.
TRAIN STOPS
So?
You wouldn't have extra pyjamas?
Wouldn't I?
I wouldn't order dessert.
I get the message.
That isn't exactly what I meant.
This is an unscheduled stop.
And two men got out of a police car
as we pulled in.
They weren't smiling.
TRAIN PULLS OUT OF STATION
You'd better tell those police
to hurry. Patience is a virtue.
I can't breathe. Just lie still.
Have you any olive oil? Olive oil?
I feel like a sardine(!)
KNOCKING
Come in.
State Police.
Your name? >
Eve Kendall. Is anything wrong?
- There was a man at your table.
- Yes?
But I never saw him before.
- Is this the man?
- I think so, but the photo
isn't very clear.
It's a wire photo from New York.
- He's wanted for murder.
- Good heavens, no!
- You left together.
- At the same time, not together.
- What did you talk about?
- Talk about?
You were talking to Thornhill.
- Is that his name?
- He didn't tell you?
He didn't tell me anything.
We chatted about different kinds
of food,
train travel versus plane travel...
Rather innocuous considering he was
a fugitive from justice.
Who did he kill?
- Did he say where he was going?
- No, I assumed Chicago.
Do you think he got off?
If you see him again, Miss...
Kendall.
I'm going to bed soon, so I doubt
I'll see him, or anyone, tonight.
We'll be in the observation car.
It's comforting to know that.
Good night.
(Still breathing?)
Hurry up, or get me a snorkel!
I'm looking for the can opener.
I stole it from the porter.
Hello, there. Hello.
H'mmm.
Tell me. Why are you so good to me?
Shall I climb up and tell you why?
You know, I've been thinking.
It's not safe for you to roam
around Chicago looking for
this George Kaplain.
You'll be caught the moment you
show your face. Such a nice face.
Don't you think it would be
a better idea if you stayed
in my hotel room
while I located him for you?
I can't let you get involved.
It's dangerous. I'm a big girl.
Yeah...and in all the right places,
too.
This is ridiculous. You know that,
don't you? Ye-es.
I mean, we've hardly met.
That's right.
How do I know you aren't
a murderer? You don't.
Maybe you're planning to murder me.
Here. Tonight.
Shall I?
Please do.
Beats flying, doesn't it?
We should stop. Immediately.
I ought to know more about you.
What more could you know?
You're an advertising man,
that's all I know. That's right.
M'mmm, train's a little unsteady.
Who isn't?
What else do you know?
You've got taste in clothes,
in food...
And taste in women.
I like YOUR flavour.
You're very clever with words.
Can probably make them do anything
for you.
Sell people things they don't need,
make women who don't know you
fall in love with you.
I'm beginning to think
I'm underpaid.
DOOR BUZZER SOUNDS
BUZZER SOUNDS AGAIN
Look out.
Oh, porter.
Don't bother
with the washroom.
Yes, ma'am.
I found this. Is it yours?
I'll wait outside.
Thank you.
DOOR CLOSES
wherever you are.
The porter...
So I see.
Now...
Where were we? Here...
Ohh, ye-es...
Nice of him to have opened the bed.
Ye-es.
Only ONE bed. Ye-es...
It's a good omen, don't you think?
Wonderful.
You know what that means? H'mm...
What? Tell me.
YOU're going to sleep on the floor.
A message from the lady in 39-01.
Keep walking, I'll catch up. Ma'am.
Anything to report, Miss Kendall?
Why, yes.
I had a fine night's sleep.
Have you seen that man again?
Mr Thorniecroft?
Thorn-HILL.
Oh, no. No.
I'm awfully sorry.
But good luck to you both.
(How we doing?)
I may collapse at any moment.
First we have to run
the gauntlet. Look.
I'm accustomed to having a load on.
But what have you got
in these bags? Bowling balls(!)
Which one of these has my suit
in it? The small one.
That ought to do it a lot of good.
Mr Kaplain won't mind the wrinkles.
If he's still there.
What time is it? 9.10. 9.10!
He may have left the hotel by now.
I'll call him for you.
I can do it. A Red-cap
in a phone booth - a bit suspicious.
Well, what will you tell him?
That you want to see him right away,
terribly urgent, no explanations.
While I'm calling, you can change
your clothes.
And where do you propose
I do THAT?
I sort of had the men's room
in mind. Did you now?
You're the smartest girl
I ever spent the night with.
I think we made it.
Where did he go?
Which way did he go?
He went up THAT way.
TANNOY:
'New York special departing
at 10am for Michigan City.'
What took you so long?
Big face, small razor.
Did you get Kaplain? Yes.
What did he say? He'll see you.
But NOT at the hotel
under any circumstances. Where?
I've got it written down. Thanks.
You take the Greyhound bus
for Indianapolis at two. Get off
at Prairie Stop, Highway 41.
Prairie Stop, Highway 41.
It's an hour and a half drive.
I'll rent a car. No car.
Mr Kaplain said "bus". All right.
What do I do when I get there?
Wait. He'll be there at 3.30.
How will I know him? He'll know you.
You made the Chicago papers.
Have you reset your watch?
Yes, I did that.
What's the matter? Matter?
Yes, you seem tense. You'd better
go before the police see you.
We WILL see each other again?
..Sometime, I'm sure.
I never had a moment to thank you
properly. Please go. Yes, but...
I've got to pick up my bags now.
These are the checks
for the cases.
Wait!
Please...
They're coming!
Hi.
Hot day.
I've seen worse.
Are you supposed to be meeting
someone here? Waiting for the bus.
Due any minute. Oh.
Some of them crop-duster pilots
get rich - if they live long enough.
Then...your name isn't Kaplain?
Can't say it is, cos it ain't.
BUS ARRIVES >
Right on time.
That's funny. That plane's dusting
crops where there ain't none.
MACHINE-GUN FIRE
COUGHING AND SPLUTTERING
TRUCK HORN BLARES
BRAKES SQUEAL
Get out of here!
The other tank may blow!
What happened?
Hey!
Come back! Hey! Come back!
Come ba-a-ack!
Yes?
Could you let me have Mr Kaplain's
room number, please? Kaplain?
I think he checked out...
Checked out? Yes, at 7.10
this morning.
7.10? Are you sure? Yes.
He left a forwarding address:
Hotel Sheraton Johnson,
Rapid City. 7.10 ?
I got a message from him
at nine... What's that?
Nothing. Nothing.
Sorry to bother you again. Uh-huh?
Miss Eve Kendall's expecting me.
She's in Room 4-something.
I've forgotten the number.
She's in 463. That's right. Thanks.
Hello.
Surprised?
Yes.
There's no getting rid of me.
I could use a drink.
I have some Scotch.
With water, no ice.
How did it go today?
The meeting with Kaplain?
Uh-huh.
He didn't show up. Oh?
It's funny, isn't it? Why funny?
After all those involved directions
he gave you on the phone...
Maybe I copied them down wrong.
I don't think you got them wrong.
I think you sent me
to the right place all right.
Why don't you call him back again?
I did. He checked out.
Went to South Dakota.
South Dakota?
Rapid City.
Well, what will you do next?
I haven't made my mind up yet.
It may depend on you.
On me?
Sure. You're my little helper,
aren't you?
Thank you. To us -
a long and lasting friendship.
Meaning, from now on, I'm not
going to let you out of my sight.
I'm afraid you'll have to. Oh, no.
I DO have plans of my own.
And YOU do have problems.
Wouldn't it be nice if my problems
and your plans were connected (?)
Then we could always stay close,
not have to go off in separate
directions - togetherness.
PHONE RINGS
Go ahead. It can't be for me.
RING
Hello?
No. Not yet, I'm not ready.
What time?
I'll meet you. What's the address?
Yes. Goodbye.
Business? Yes.
Industrial designing business?
Mm-hm.
All work and no play...
A girl like you should be enjoying
herself instead of taking calls
from clients.
What about having dinner with me?
You can't afford to be seen.
Have it up here. Nice and cosy.
No, I...
I can't.
I insist.
I want you to do a...favour for me.
A BIG favour. Name it.
..I want you to leave right now.
Stay far away from me
and don't come near me again.
We're NOT going to get involved.
Last night was last night.
That's all.
There won't be anything more
between us.
So, please...goodbye...
Good luck...no conversation...
just leave.
Right away? Yes.
No questions asked? ..Yes.
No. I can't do that.
Please. After dinner.
Now! After dinner. Fair's fair.
All right. On one condition...
that you let the hotel valet
do something with this suit first.
You belong in a stockyard like that.
The phone.
Hello. Valet service, please.
Valet?
This is room... Where are we?
463.
Four-six-three.
How quickly can you get a suit
sponged and pressed?
20 minutes? Fine.
OK, 463.
He'll be right up.
Better take your things off.
Yeah.
Now, what could a man do with
his clothes off for 20 minutes?
You can always take a cold shower.
When I was a little boy
I wouldn't even let my mother
undress me. You're a BIG boy now.
How does a girl like you
GET to be a girl like you?
Lucky, I guess.
Not lucky, naughty, up to no good.
Ever kill anyone?
Because I bet you could tease
a man to death without
half-trying.
DOOR BUZZER
Be with you in a minute.
Trousers, please.
Thank you.
I'll take that cold shower
after all.
Good.
AUCTIONEER:
..original gilt finish
upholstered in pure silk damask.
How much may I say to start?
What am I bid?
100 is bid. Thank you.
150. Say the 200...
200 is bid, say three...
I have 300,
400...
450 is bid. Can I hear 500?
500. Can I say the five?
Fair warning and last call...
Sold to Mr Stone. 450.
And now Lot 103.
Ah, this lovely settee...
In excellent condition.
Please start the bidding.
How much? 800 is offered.
Say the nine. Go 900.
900 is bid. 1,000?
1,000, thank you. Say eleven...
The three of you together -
a picture only Charles Adams could
draw. Good evening, Mr Kaplain.
Before we start name-calling,
can I know yours?
You disappoint me, sir.
I was about to say that to her.
I considered you a shrewd fellow.
What possessed you to come
blundering in? Interest in art?
Yes. The art of survival.
Have you poured any drunks lately?
He followed me here from the hotel.
He was in your room?
Sure. Isn't everybody?
Say the two...
Do I hear the two? 200.
Do I hear the three? 300.
Do I hear the four? 400?
400 is bid. Say the five?
And I thought you only collected
corpses(!) 500.
I'll bet you paid plenty for THIS.
700.
She's worth EVERY dollar of it.
Take it from me.
She puts EVERYTHING into her work.
Sold. Mr Vandamm at 700.
Oh, Mr Vandamm!
Has anyone ever told you
you overplay your various roles?
First, the outraged Madison Ave
man, claiming mistaken identity,
then the fugitive from justice
trying to clear his name;
now you play the peevish lover
stunned by jealousy.
Seems to me you could do with more
training from the actors studio(!)
The only performance that will
satisfy you is when I play dead.
Your very next role.
You'll be quite convincing.
AUCTIONEER: 375 I'm bid...
I wonder
what subtle form of manslaughter
is next on the programme.
Am I to be dropped into a vat
of molten steel, for a skyscraper?
Or will this female kiss me
and poison me to death?
Who are you kidding?
You have NO feelings to hurt.
Mr Kaplain, we've had just about
enough of you. Send for the police.
That's the last thing you'd want,
me in the hands of the police.
There's something I might tell them.
That's why she hustled me.
I'll have a chance of survival
with the police.
Good night, sweetheart.
Don't think it wasn't nice(!)
1,300...?
May I hear 1,300?
Do I hear 1,300?
Last call.
Sold. 1,200 dollars. Thank you.
And now, catalogue number 109.
This early 17th century master
will enhance any collection.
What is your pleasure?
One thousand I have...
1,250 I have.
Now 1,500.
1,500 is bid. Thank you.
I have 1,750.
I have 2,000. Do I hear 25?
I have 2,250.
I have 2,250, once...
Twice...
Last call... 1,500!
The bid is 2,250, sir.
Well, I still say 1,500.
2,250.
Do I hear 25?
2,250, once...
Sold! For 2,250.
Twenty-two fifty!
For that cromo!
GASPS
Number 110 in the catalogue.
A Louis Quinze carved
and gilded chair.
Will someone start at 750, please?
It's a fake!
CRIES OF DISGUST
Well, YOU're no fake.
You're a genuine idiot! Thank you.
Could I ask the gentleman, to join
the spirit of the proceedings?
All right. I'll start it at eight.
800. Thank you.
1,000 is bid. Go 12? 11.
11 is bid. Thank you. Go 12?
Who'll say 12?
11 once... Who'll say 12?
11 twice... 12.
Go 13?
Who'll say 13? 13 dollars.
You mean 1,300, sir.
No... No, I MEAN 13 dollars!
LAUGHTER
I-I have 1,200.
Go 13. Who'll say 13?
Who'll say 1,250?
1,200 once...
Twice...
2,000!
GASPS
2,000?
2,100!
I-I'm sorry, sir...
Make it 2,500!
Would the gentleman
PLEASE co-operate?
The bid was 1,200.
2,500.
MURMURS FROM BUYERS
I have...
What was it?
1,200.
I have 1,200, once...
Twice... 3,000!
Sold for 1,200!
That's unfair! I...
You'd better leave, sir.
Oh, no, you...
GASPS OF HORROR
What took you so long? Let's go.
Wait! I haven't finished bidding.
Three thousand!
Too bad, old man. Keep trying.
Not so rough!
Handle with care, fellows.
I'm valuable property.
I want to thank you gentlemen
for saving my life. Thank you.
Save it for the Station House.
Let's have some good cheer. You're
heroes. Don't you know who I am?
We'll find out when we book you
for being drunk and disorderly.
That's chicken feed.
You've hit the jackpot.
"Chicago Police capture
United Nations Killer."
I'm Roger Thornhill.
It's HIM.
Congratulations, men.
Yeah...
This is 1055. >
We have a man here, Thornhill.
Code 76. Wanted by NYPD. >
Positive ID. >
Absolutely.
Michigan Ave, proceeding north
to 42nd Precinct. >
What?
Come again.
Are you sure?
OK. Right. Yeah, I've got it.
1055, off and clear.
Where are we going?
Airport.
For what?
Orders!
The airport! I want to be taken
to Police Headquarters.
Why do you think I sent for you?
HE sent for us(!)
Sit back. I want to go
to Police Headquarters.
I'm a mad killer on the loose!
You should be ashamed of yourself.
TANNOY:
'Announcing Flight 29,
arriving at Gate 12.'
He said right here.
Does anyone mind if I sit down?
TANNOY:
'Final call, American Airlines
Flight 48.
'Now boarding at gate no 14.'
Ah! I thought I'd never make it.
Getting old.
Thank you.
This way, Mr Thornhill. Wait...
We haven't much time. This way.
I don't think I caught your name.
I don't think I pitched it.
You're police, or is it FBI?
FBI, CIA, ONI, we're all in
the same alphabet soup.
I had nothing to do with that
United Nations killing. We know.
Then why did you let the police
chase me? We try not to interfere
with the police.
Now it's become necessary. Ah.
I take it I will be cleared?
Do walk faster, or we'll miss
the plane. Where are we going?
Rapid City, South Dakota.
What for!?
It's near Mount Rushmore.
I've SEEN Mount Rushmore.
So is your friend Mr Vandamm.
Vandamm?!
Rather a formidable gentleman, eh?
And that little tramp with him?
Miss Kendall? His mistress.
What's Vandamm up to?
You could say he's an importer/
exporter. Of what?
Oh...government secrets, perhaps.
Why don't you grab him? We want to
know more about his organisation.
What's this to do with Mt Rushmore?
Vandamm is there. We think he's
leaving the country tomorrow night.
You going to stop him? No.
Why are we going?
To set his mind at ease
about Kaplain. Oh, you!
YOU're George Kaplain.
There is NO such person as Kaplain.
What do you mean? I've been
in his hotel, tried his clothes.
He doesn't exist.
Which is why I want you to go on
being him for the next 24 hours.
We'll discuss it on the plane.
PLANE ENGINE DROWNS OUT VOICES
..You started the decoy business
without me, YOU finish it.
Well, we might have... You ought
to give me a medal
instead of asking me to be a target
so your agent doesn't get shot at!
Not shot at, found out. Once
found out, they're as good as dead.
Thanks to you, suspicion is already
forming. Thanks to me?
I'm an advertising man,
NOT a red herring.
I've got a secretary, a mother
and two ex-wives dependent upon me.
I can't afford
to be slightly killed.
The answer is no.
Is that final? Yes.
Goodbye. Goodbye. Then there's
no need to talk about Miss Kendall,
of whom you obviously disapprove?
You're using sex like a fly-swatter.
I don't suppose it matters to you
that she was forced to do
what she did to protect herself.
From what? Exposure.
Assassination.
You see, Mr Thornhill, she...
she's one of our agents.
Oh, no...
I'm afraid you HAVE put her
in a very dangerous situation.
And much more than her life
is at stake.
Suppose they don't come?
They'll come.
I don't like the way
Teddy Roosevelt is looking at me.
He's giving you a word of caution:
"Speak softly, carry a big stick."
Or NOT to go through
with this scheme.
Perhaps he doesn't know that
you caused our problem.
I don't accept that.
If you hadn't been so attractive
to Miss Kendall... And vice-versa.
..Vandamm wouldn't be suspicious.
It's clear she is
emotionally involved.
AND with a man who's a government
agent. Are you saying I am
irresistible?
I'm trying to remind you that
YOU have a responsibility to help
up until he leaves the country.
All right.
And AFTER tonight?
My blessings on you both.
Here they are.
Good afternoon, Mr Kaplain.
Not her.
Did I misunderstand you about
bringing her here? No, you didn't.
I suppose my call surprised you?
No. I knew the police
would release you.
By the way, my compliments
on your colourful exit
from the auction. Thank you.
Now what little drama
are we here for?
I don't believe you've invited me
to these gay surroundings to come
to a business arrangement.
Well, I not only know WHEN
you are leaving the country,
but your ultimate destination.
You wouldn't care to carry
my bags(!)
I would be interested in the price
just the same. The price?
For doing nothing to stop you.
How much did you have in mind?
The girl.
I want the girl to get
what's coming to her.
I'll see there's enough
pinned on her
to make her life uncomfortable.
Do that and I'll let you go.
She really did get under your skin.
We're talking about YOUR skin. I'm
offering you a chance to save it.
To EXCHANGE it.
Put it any way you like.
I'm curious, Mr Kaplain.
How did you reach the deduction
that my feelings for Miss Kendall
had deteriorated to SUCH an extent?
I don't deduce, I observe.
Philip, if you don't mind,
I'm going back to the house.
Just a second, you. Stay away!
Stay away from me. Let go!
Let go of me! Save the phoney tears.
You little fool!
Just stay away from me.
(Let her go.)
Don't touch anything.
Mr Thornhill.
Don't be long.
Hello.
Are you all right?
Yes, I think so.
I asked the Professor
if I could see you.
Oh?
There's not much time.
Isn't there?
I wanted to tell...
I mean, apologise...
No need.
I understand.
All in the line of duty.
I DID treat you miserably.
I hated you for it.
I didn't want you to go on
thinking that...
I-I used some pretty harsh words.
I'm sorry.
They hurt deeply. If I'd known...
I couldn't tell you. Of course not.
Could I?
No, I guess not.
You didn't get hurt.
I'm SO relieved.
Of course I was hurt! I mean
in the cafeteria when I shot you
with the blanks. Oh, THAT.
You did it rather well. Yes,
I thought I was quite graceful.
Considering it's not really
your kind of work.
Well, I got into it by accident.
What's YOUR excuse?
I met Philip Vandamm at a party
and saw only his charm.
Oh.
I had nothing to do that weekend,
so I decided to fall in love.
That's nice.
Eventually, the Professor and
his colleagues approached me with
some sordid details about Philip.
They told me that my relationship
with him made me uniquely valuable
to them.
So, you became a Girl Scout?
Maybe it was the first time anyone
asked me to do anything worthwhile.
Has life been like THAT?
Mm-hm.
How come?
..Men like you.
What's wrong with men like me?
They don't believe in marriage.
I've been married twice.
See what I mean?
I may go back to hating you.
It was more fun.
Goodbye, darling.
Wait a minute. Not so soon.
I have to go and convince them
I took the long way round.
Couldn't we stand like this
for just a few hours?
You're supposed to be dying.
I've never felt more alive.
Whose side are you on?
Yours always.
Please don't undermine my resolve
when I need it most.
Oh, well, I guess it's off
to hospital for me and back
to danger for you.
It's much safer now, thanks to you,
my darling decoy.
Don't thank me. I can't stand
it. All right, I won't.
After your friend Vandamm
takes off, you and I will get
together in private.
You know that can't be. It CAN be.
Well, he HAS told you, hasn't he?
Told me WHAT?
We better get moving.
What didn't you tell me? Professor?
She's going off with Vandamm
tonight on the plane.
She's going off with Vandamm?
That's why we set up the charade.
So that Vandamm HAD to take her.
But...
She can be valuable to us
over there. You lied to me!
I needed your help.
Don't be angry. You can't do it.
She HAS to!
Nobody HAS to do anything.
I don't like these games.
War is hell, even a cold one.
If you can't lick the Vandamms
of this world without using
girls like her,
perhaps you need to LOSE
a few cold wars!
I'm afraid we're already
doing that.
I won't let you go.
Don't spoil everything.
RADIO:
'..shot Mr Kaplain twice in front of
scores of horrified men, women
and children.
'Witnesses described the women
as an attractive blonde
in her late twenties.
'Kaplain was rushed to hospital
in a critical condition.
'Kaplain was tentatively identified
as an employee of the Federal
Government.
'A bus-boy in the Mount Rushmore
cafeteria...'
Here we are. Hello.
Slacks, shirt, and these.
Thank you.
They'll do for you around here
for the next couple of days.
Couple of days?
Hey! What? What's this?
That's where I hit the chair
during that phoney fall.
Otherwise feeling all right?
Fine. Considering your driver
has a sledge-hammer for a hand.
Sorry. I deserved it. I guess
I deserve that locked door, too.
If you were seen it could prove
fatal for Miss Kendall.
I've begun to forget her already.
Good.
Better that way.
Inside of an hour, she'll be gone.
Oh. How's everything
in Rapid City?
Fine. Mr Kaplain's shooting
has acquired the authority
of the printed word.
Everyone's been co-operating well.
Including me.
I'm co-operative. I'm grateful.
Care to do me a favour? Anything.
I'd like a drink. Can you get me
some bourbon? A pint will do.
Can I join you? If you do,
you'd better make it a quart.
See you in a few minutes.
What a m...!
Stop! Oh, excuse me.
Stop...
Ah-ah-ah...
Sure you don't want me to take you
up there? Never mind. This is fine.
CAR DRAWING UP >
EVE:
I just lost my head.
I'm not trying to make you feel
better. I mean it.
I didn't mean it...
He wanted to destroy you.
You had to protect yourself.
Soon we will be off and I shall
dedicate myself to you.
What's the situation, Leonard?
About the plane, you mean?
Yes. What's the latest report?
On course, 6,000 and descending.
We've got ten minutes. At the most.
And... I wonder if I may have
a few moments of parting
with you, sir. Certainly.
In private? I'll get my things.
Well, Leonard,
how does one say goodbye
to one's right arm?
You may wish you had cut it off.
Mmm?
I know how fond you are
of Miss Kendall,
and I find this a terrible thing...
She's not to be trusted...
COIN CLATTERS ON GROUND
COIN HITS GLASS
It couldn't have been anything.
YOU must have had doubts about her.
And still do.
Rubbish. Why else
didn't you tell her
that the microfilm is hidden here?
You're trying to poison my mind.
The truth... The truth?
It's innuendo!
Call it my "women's intuition"
but I've never trusted neatness.
She shot him in a moment of anger.
You were there. You saw it. Yes.
And thereby wrapped everything up
into a neat bundle(!)
A - She removed any doubts you had
about her devotion.
B - She gave herself an urgent
reason to be taken with you.
You know what I think...?
I think you're jealous.
I'm VERY touched. Very...
Leonard...?
GUN FIRES
The gun she shot Kaplain with.
It's an old Gestapo trick -
shoot one of your own people
to show you're not one of them.
THEY'VE just used blank cartridges.
DOOR OPENS
What was that noise?
Yes, we wondered what it was, too.
Didn't we, Leonard?
Hurry up. It's almost time to go.
In a moment.
DOOR CLOSES >
You're not taking her with you?
Of course I am.
Like our friends, I too
believe in neatness, Leonard.
This matter is best disposed of
from a great height, over water.
How about a little champagne
before we go?
I'd love it. It'll kill the time.
Over the rocks would be fine.
Sure.
CLINK OF GLASSES >
Thank you. To YOU, my dear,
and all the lovely moments
we've had together.
There he is.
PLANE DRAWS CLOSER
Jump in, Leonard.
The champagne's fine.
There's no time.
You always were a spoilsport.
It would please me if you would
think of me as being with you,
if only in spirit. I shall.
He's heading out
on the north leg.
I guess he'll take
a long, slow descent.
Couldn't ask for a better night.
Possibilities unlimited.
Ah, there he goes,
starting his turn.
We'd better get moving.
He'll land in a few minutes.
Come along, Eve. All right.
Oh! I think I left my earrings
upstairs. I'll be right down.
Darling. Come, out by the window.
Roger, you'll RUIN everything.
They know about the fake shooting.
What?
And that figure is full
of microfilm. THAT'S how
he's been getting it.
Miss Kendall!
Don't get on that plane.
You and your husband will be over
the Canadian border by tomorrow.
Thank you very much, sir.
God bless you.
I'll wait, sir.
Take care.
Thanks very much.
PLANE CAN BE HEARD OVERHEAD
DOOR CLOSES
Stay where you are.
Sit down.
As soon as the plane leaves,
Mr Leonard will be back.
PLANE ABOUT TO LAND
PLANE TAXIS UP RUNWAY
What is it?
I was wondering about my earrings.
They'll turn up.
Say goodbye to my sister for me.
Thank her for playing Mrs Townsend.
Thank your knife-throwing friend.
That's about all, Leonard.
Get that figure back from her.
The housekeeper had me pinned down
with that silly gun of yours -
I only just realised.
You've got the pumpkin. Yes.
We're on top of the monument.
What will we do? Climb down.
We can't!
Here they come. We have no choice.
If we ever get out of this alive,
we'll go to New York on the train.
Is that a proposition?
It's a proposal, sweetie.
What happened to the first
two marriages?
My wives divorced me. Why?
They said I led too dull a life.
Are you all right?
OK. Come on. Come on, get up.
Come on.
Aaaah!
Aaah! >
Help.
Help me.
GUNSHOT
Thank you, sergeant.
That wasn't very sporting.
Reach. Now. I'm...trying.
I've got you. I can't make it...
Yes, you CAN. Come on. Liar...
Come along, Mrs Thornhill.
This is silly. I know,
but I'm sentimental.